I remind you that this peritoneum develops at the same time as this phase of development
of the integration of the external coelom into an internal coelom.
This is the primitive establishment of my peritoneum.
First, I have polarity; I have information about my neural tube,
I have the growth of this neural tube organized in space and time
by the fluidic reorganization of my embryo, that is, the early development
of my embryo.
my primitive aortas, it's all part of the research
to bring it back to its midline.
I do everything to return to myself.
And my axis that I will return to is this aorta.
The peritoneum responds to this development.
It is the end goal; it is the expression of this development.
I have the amniotic cavity, the yolk sac,
the embryonic stalk, and all around here,
all around, which wraps.
This is what we call the external coelom.
In the next phase of development, we will see how this external coelom is
integrated into an internal coelom.
This occurs synchronously between the establishment of my
primitive digestive tube
and the formation of the wrapping around it, my visceral peritoneum
and my parietal peritoneum.
And between my visceral peritoneum,
and my parietal peritoneum, there is a fluid that integrates, which comes from the
external coelom to
become the internal coelom, which will later be called the intraperitoneal fluid.
There are no
intraperitoneal organs; there are only peritonealized organs. Few
exceptions exist in
women where there is an opening between the peritoneum and the outside world
due to the organization
of the fallopian tubes. That’s why we can have a...
ectopic pregnancy. The uterus is just a concentration of posterior parietal peritoneum
that condenses, and the lines that will form here will create the tubes
toward the opening of my peritoneal cavity. The amniotic cavity, the yolk sac
and the embryonic stalk. There is this significant growth
of the whole,
it grows and organizes and delineates.
Then, to help us, we will make a cut, we will turn this cut toward us, and
so it's the same drawing, but in another dimension, where this time, I
see my amniotic cavity, my yolk sac, I see the
notochordal process, which is one of the subtle engines for
development, I see the formation of my neural tube, which is the engine
for growth.
It is the one that directs by its explosion, but which is oriented in its growth
by the notochord.
There is this amniotic cavity that comes completely through the neural tube and through my aortas
which will develop here on both sides at the origin of my neural tube,
oriented and organized in the space of development of this embryo.
The significant growth in the
form of a groove of my embryo,
the aortas appearing, the closure of my neural tube, slowly
we don't see it,
but the rapprochement of my aortas will occur because they will not grow at the same
rate; we see them, and at the moment of this rapprochement, you
see, they were there,
they have started to move towards the center, these two tubes bring the information, but do not grow
at all at the same speed, and everything around grows, and the only possible result
is that it comes from the water.
they move toward the center, which reorganizes the longitudinal axis of the embryo,
which reorganizes the global arrangement that means, okay, but I'm coming toward where I’m drawn
it's like
an attraction that takes place that orients this movement, and now there is
a space being created with the
somatopleure, the splanchnopleure and at the same time we see the neural tube, the rapprochement of my
aortas and we see the formation
at the same time, at the same moment, of my developing digestive tube.
And we see in this slice that the fluid that is here
begins little by little to be enclosed here,
to integrate into a space here.
And in this space, if we continue the development,
what is very important, and not expressed in this drawing,
is to see this in a growth process.
Look at the formation of my tube,
and look at this movement here.
of my amniotic cavity that comes completely wrapped
on the sides,
but also toward the front, toward the back, like a balloon that is
tied here and which
wraps around in front. And it is in this movement here, by my aortas that slow down,
by my notochord that organizes the story, I have the integration of
my external coelom.
Into an internal coelom, this is a section that will be located near my umbilical cord.
I can make the same section further, here or here.
This image slightly changes.
Either I have this connection with the future umbilical cord, the remnant of
the yolk sac,
which will integrate with the embryonic stalk,
or another time, another movement, where I will just see the integration
of my peritoneal cavity.
Don't forget, I am connected by my umbilical cord.
We will make the same cut, but this time further forward.
And at this level, I will truly see the integration.
Always the same movement.
So my amniotic cavity is very important,
because not only was it a little pouch that appeared,
but it will completely invade the space.
And now we arrive at
the image, where it closes completely there, at this stage, and
I am here. I have the integration
of my external coelom into an internal coelom. I have the integration
of the external coelom into an
internal coelom. This is an important image because we will see that your
digestive tube,
not only is it filled with bacteria.
A genome contains information from your environment.
So it even contains genetic information.
It is filled with genes that contribute to your own development.
A holobiont that encompasses all this genetic environment,
that you begin to prepare, to integrate,
which will be completely energized at the time of birth.
Where you will completely prepare the humus.
the flora that will completely explode in its dynamics,
but upon which you rely for your development.
And we know that these genes that participate in your flora
interact with your brain, they interact with your thoughts.
You think through the type of bacteria you have.
Hence the importance of finding an adequate setting, an environment.
where you feel good.
The environment in which I evolve also makes me evolve,
because all of this contributes to your genetics and your epigenetics,
that is, to your ability for permanent adaptation.
First image of your peritoneal cavity,
of this peritoneum that is forming.
It has both a metabolic function,
it has a protective function,
it has a mechanical function.
It participates in your motricity, it participates in your mobility
and it is integrated by your motility.
Its origin is mesoderm, meaning it has a mechanical function,
a supporting function, and a mobility function. One of its roles, there
is a type
of cellular specialization at the mesoderm level, called mesothelial cells,
which will enable...
the peritonea to capture information inter
- and intra-peritoneal.
This is a very large serous membrane.
I believe it is approximately 2 square meters.